<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="peter.kliem@jaret.de">Peter Kliem</author>
    <title>jaret timebars (gantt chart and timeline widget/control for SWT and Swing)</title>
  </properties>
 <head>
    <meta name="keywords" content="java, component, widget, Swing, SWT, Gantt chart" />
  </head>
 <body>
    <section name="de.jaret.util.ui.timebars">
		<p>
			Note: This site is a fork in support of <a href="https://jaret.de/timebars/">the original Jaret Timebars project</a>,
			intended to be a home for bug fixes until the original project resumes development.
			Much of the original content is left as is.
			The goal is to provide compatibility with the original as much as reasonably possible,
			though we unfortunately did have a breaking change with the first release of this fork.
			See the <a href="status.html">status page</a>.
		</p>
		<p>
		The jaret timebars package contains a viewer for a data model containing rows of intervals. The viewer displays the
		intervals in a Gantt chart fashion. The viewer is implemented for Swing and the SWT toolkit using a delegate for
		most of the work. <b>Priority of the development is the SWT version! Swing has mostly caught up with version 1.30.</b>
		</p>
		<p>If you want to know about new versions you can <b>follow the 
		timebars on twitter</b>: <a href="http://twitter.com/jaret_timebars">http://twitter.com/jaret_timebars</a>
		</p>
		<p> If you like you can comment and rate the timebars component at 
		<a href="http://www.eclipseplugincentral.com/Web_Links-index-req-ratelink-lid-818.html">Eclipse Plugin Central</a>.
		</p>
		<p>
		Features include:
		<ul>
			<li>
				rendering is done by renderers allowing a complete customization (simple default renderers are supplied). Renderers may
				support printing.
			</li>
			<li>
				follows the mvc pattern
			</li>
			<li>
				available for SWT and Swing (lower priority)
			</li>
			<li>
				additional components: marker (vertical), synchronizer for multiple viewers
			</li>
			<li>
				flexible selection model
			</li>
			<li>
				supports hierarchical view 
			</li>
			<li>
				supports relations between intervals 
			</li>
			<li>
				supports visual editing (dragging of intervals, resizing of intervals) 
			</li>
			<li>
				supports horizontal (classic gantt) and vertical orientation (i.e. for a calendar view) 
			</li>
			<li>
				region selection 
			</li>
			<li>
				variable time scale including "breaks" in the timeline 
			</li>
			<li>
				addon package supports using the timebars component in an Eclipse RCP (saving the viewstate) and
				adds synchronization support towards the jaret table allowing combined visualization
				of tabular and timed data 
			</li>
		</ul>
		</p>
		<subsection name="Dual licensing">
		<p>
			The package is licensed under the GNU Public License (see <a href="license.html">LICENSE</a>), with exceptions allowing
			the usage in other free projects licensed under EPL 1.0, CPL 1.0, LGPL 2.0/2.1, Apache 2.0, or CDDL.
			If you are interested in a commercial license for use in closed source projects check <a href="commercial.html">here</a>
			or contact info@jaret.de (please prepend the subject with "[jaret]").
		</p>
		</subsection>
		<subsection name="Download / javadoc">
		<p>
			There are several different packages available for download 
			(please note that you will also need the <a href="/jaretutil">jaretutil</a> package):
		</p>
			<table>
				<tr>
					<td>
						<a href="data/timebars-1.49-src.zip">timebars-1.49-src.zip</a>
					</td>
					<td>
						Recommended download: Contains the complete project for Swing and SWT, including example code. Depends on 
						de.jaret.util (0.32)!
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>
						<a href="data/timebars-1.49-bin.zip">timebars-1.49-bin.zip</a>
					</td>
					<td>
						Contains jar including Swing and SWT version. Depends on 
						de.jaret.util (0.32)!
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>
						<a href="documentation/timebars.pdf">overview documentation (PDF)</a>
					</td>
					<td>
						Overview documentation as a PDF (html: see <a href="documentation/timebars.html">HTML documentation</a>)
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>
						<a href="../timebars.addon/index.html">timebars addon package</a>
					</td>
					<td>
						Addon package
					</td>
				</tr>
			</table>
		<p>
			View the javadoc here: <a href="apidocs/index.html">apidoc</a>.
		</p>
		</subsection>
		<subsection name="Screenshots and screen casts">
		<p>
			There are some screenshots and screencasts available <a href="tb_screenshots.html">here.</a> Remember that the rendering is done
			by renderers that can easily be customized.
		</p>
		</subsection>
		<subsection name="Status and platforms">
		<p>
			The TimeBarViewer is production quality - as long as the supported features serve the purposes
			of the application (In fact it is in production use since Q1/2005). With the 1.0 version the SWT version 
			is stable.
			<b>However: This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY;
			without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.</b>
		</p>
		<p>
			The Swing version of the TimeBarViewer should run on every platform supporting Java 1.8 since 1.50, or 1.5 before that.
			The main testing of the SWT component was done on Win32.
			Tests have also been performed on Linux with the GTK+ version of SWT and on Mac OS X. Due to the
			nature of the SWT toolkit it can not be guaranteed that the component will work on all platforms. 
		</p>
		</subsection>
		<subsection name="Bugs">
		<p>
			All components have bugs.
			To report issues on this fork, please see <a href="https://github.com/intranetmouse/jarettimebars/issues">the issues page on github</a>.
		</p>
</subsection>
</section>
  </body>
</document>