<document>
	<properties>
		<author email="peter.kliem@jaret.de">Peter Kliem</author>
		<title>jaret timebars changelog</title>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<section name="changelog for de.jaret.util.ui.timebars">
			<subsection name="Note for Swing users">
				The SWT Version is leading. However the the swing version has catched up to provide nearly the same features.
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2009-06-23 version 1.35">
				<ul>
					<li>
						SWT: Fixed a small bug in the RelationRenderer (NullPointer under rare conditions)
					</li>
					<li>
						Added synchronization for the y axis width in the synchronizer
					</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2009-05-20 version 1.34">
				<ul>
					<li>
						SWT: Fixed a small bug that could happen when displaying a context menu
					</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2009-05-07 version 1.33">
				<ul>
					<li>
						Added a feature for setting the initial displayRange when the viewer is first displayed and the width of the widget is available. 
						See <code>setInitialDisplayRange</code>
					</li>
					<li>
						Fixed a bug in the DefaultTimeBarRowModel that prevented the correct update of the max date if an interval would change min AND max date.
					</li>
					<li>
						Fixed a bug in the Swing DefaultTimeScaleRenderer (refactoring artefact, thanx Ravi).
					</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2009-02-22 version 1.32">
				<ul>
					<li>
						BoxTimeScaleRenderer now scales down from years to minutes/seconds/milliseconds
					</li>
					<li>
						Swing and SWT: The DefaultTimeScaleRenderer has been replaced by a new one that scales from years to milliseconds. 
						If your application needs the old default renderer you can set the old renderer explicitly (it is still in the
						distribution: OldDefaultTimeScaleRenderer).
					</li>
					<li>
						Internal coordinate calculation will now always use milliseconds as the basis. This should not cause any problems. 
						However, if you encounter problems, please report the bug.
					</li>
					<li>
						Fixed a small bug in tooltip handling.
					</li>
					<li>
						Swing: added the IMarkerRenderer for better control of how markers are painted.
					</li>
					<li>
						Swing: added the IGlobalAssistantRenderer for misc rendering.
					</li>
					<li>
						New methods for scaling: setSecondsDisplayed(...); the scaling can be centered around a date
					</li>
					
					<li>
						GridRenderers now have to accept an ITickScalProvider to achieve a coupling between time scale renderers and the grid rendeering. 
						The default grid renderer will use the supplied tick scale provider. The BoxTimeScaleRenderer and the DefaultTimeScaleRenderes
						do implement the ITickProvider interfaces.
					</li>
					<li>
						Extended ITimeBarChangeListener: marker drags will be reported.
					</li>
					<li>
						The variable x scale feature now supports "breaking" the timescale by marking pps intervals as breaks and defining a pixel width 
						for the display. See the milli example for details (documentation follows).
					</li>
					
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2009-01-11 version 1.31">
				<ul>
					<li>
						Fixed a bug in the overlap calculations that lead to intervals not properly rendered (rendered above the row)
						in some data constellations. (Thanks Daran!)
					</li>
					<li>
						Clipping on Linux GTK seems to be implemented using only 16 bit integers. This results
						in random drawings if a high zoom factor is used in combination with long intervals or relations (the drawings
						are not really random, since they are just caused by overflowing 16 bit integers). 
						Added a workaround in the relation renderer and the sum renderer of the swt hierarchy example.
					</li>
					
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2009-01-01 version 1.30">
				<ul>
					<li>
						<b>SWING:</b> Did a lot of corrections and additions for the swing component so that it nearly
						catches up to the SWT variant:
						<ul>
							<li>
								Ported the BoxTimeScaleRenderer to Swing
							</li>
							<li>
								New Swing example: EventMonitorExample demonstrating some of the new features mentioned below.
							</li>
							<li>
								Added the title renderer for swing and supplied a simple default title renderer.
							</li>
							<li>
								Added relation rendering in the swing world (ported over the relation renderer from SWT).
							</li>
							<li>
								Added the context menu support.
							</li>
							<li>
								Fixed several minor bugs.
							</li>
						</ul>
					</li>
					<li>
						Introduced findbugs in the maven build (surprisingly low number of issues) and fixed some more important issues 
						reported (nothing really serious).
					</li>
					<li>
						Introduced the region selection: a selection that is tied to time and rows that stays present and can be used
						for several purposes. The functionality has to be enabled (<code>setRegionRectEnable</code>). Region selections can
						be done with shift+click+drag. The region selection will persist until it is cleared (<code>clearRegionRect</code>)
						or replaced by the next selection. As an example a simple zoom action has been implemented in the EventMonitorExample (Swing)
						and the SwtHierarchy example.
					</li>
					<li>
						Introduced a new listener for listening to the selection rect/region selection allowing online information 
						about ongoing
						rectangle selections: (<code>ISelectionRectListener</code>)
					</li>
					<li>
						Introduced the IMiscRenderer (Swing and SWT) that will collect rendering routines for some elements/parts in the 
						timebar viewers (to be extended over time).
					</li>
					<li>
						Added the possibility to hide the root node when using a hierarchical model (<code>setHideRoot</code>).
					</li>
					<li>
						Added the possibility to draw intervals overlapping in selected rows (<code>ITimeBarViewState.setDrawOverlapping(row)</code>).
					</li>
					<li>
						Added the option to allow dragging of markers not only in the time scale area (<code>setMarkerDraggingInDiagramArea</code>.
					</li>
					<li>
						Fixed: when using vertical orientation, optimized scrolling and timescaleposition = bottom the scale would not be scrolled.
					</li>
					<li>
					<b>Attention:(SWT)</b> Removed the deprecated stuff (registering further renderers) from the default renderer. You can easily
					register specialized renderes with the TimeBarViewer directly. 
					</li>
					<li>
						Added the possibility to enforce uniform heights/widths for intervals drawn non overlapping in the same row 
						(see <code>setUseUniformHeight</code>).
					</li>
					
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2008-11-08 version 1.29">
				<ul>
					<li>
						New methods to easy scrolling to elements: <code>void setFirstRow(TimeBarRow row)</code> scrolls to a row without 
						requiring its index. <code>void scrollIntervalToVisible(Interval interval, double horizontalRatio, double verticalRatio)</code> scrolls
						an interval to a position in the viewable area.
					</li>
					<li>
						Fixed a bug in AbstractGridRenderer (static reference to a Color that got disposed); Thanks Thomas
					</li>
					
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2008-09-20 version 1.28">
				<ul>
					<li>
						Behaviour on focussing/selecting an interval: was scroll begin to visible: this is now refined to scroll only when no part of the 
						interval is visible. Scrolling on focus change can be disabled completely (setScrollOnfocus). 
					</li>
					<li>
						improved printing when using linux: swt printer devices running on linux seem to always report 72x72dpi which
						resulted in bad output when using the standard renderers. The RendererBase now contains the method <code>getDefaultLineWidth</code>
						to get a corrected line width that will work with low resolutions.
					</li>
					
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2008-08-19 version 1.27 (not published)">
				<ul>
					<li>
						Behaviour on focussing/selecting an interval: was scroll begin to visible; now configurable if scrolling should occur
						(setScrollOnfocus). Maybe this will be replaced by a strategy if necessary.
					</li>
					
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2008-06-22 version 1.26">
				<ul>
					<li>
						Fixed: Before the first paint (sometimes) NullPointerExceptions could happen because of uninitialized layout
					</li>
					<li>
						Fixed: NullPointer in getTooltipText (sometimes)
					</li>
					<li>
						Fixed: Relation rendering: arrows when using end_end.
					</li>
					
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2008-05-29 version 1.251">
				<ul>
					<li>
						Just added a new example: The linechart example: check the screenshots.
					</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2008-05-04 version 1.25">
				<ul>
					<li>
						introduced relations between intervals and relation rendering and selecting. (IRelationalInterval, 
						IIntervalRelation, IRelationRenderer, implementations thereof). There is a default implementation of the IRelationRenderer
						that is not setup by default (RelationRenderer). Changes have been made to the selection model 
						(can now contain selected IIntervalRelations) and the selection provider (can now have relations in the structured 
						selection). Unless you use relations you will not have to make changes to existing code.
						The default relation renderer does not support vertical orientation. The usage
						can be studied in the SwtHierarchyExample.
						The relations are observables but have not been added to be observed by the viewer (this would have introduced 
						major API changes), so for now a redraw has to be triggered when the relation itself changes (this is most 
						probably a rare case). 
						
					</li>
					<li>
						fixed a small bug in the box time scale renderer (week label included first day of the next week). Bug has been 
						fixed in the jaret utils package (Thanx Thomas)
					</li>
					<li>
					</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2008-04-25 version 1.24">
				<ul>
					<li>
						added some changes to the row selection behaviour (shift-click range select, toggle mode for row selections
						that can be set on the selection model for simulating check box selections). Check box selections and the toggle
						mode can be seen in the swt overlap example (activate in the control panel). 
					</li>
					<li>
						the rendering of row selection and highlighting has been moved to the grid renderer (so it is better customizable). This obviously
						breaks the API. For a quick fix reserving the current behaviour just extend AbstractGridRenderer when you have your implemented 
						own. The grid renderer interface will be a bit more extended in future versions to support some other things that have not
						been easy customizable. The getters/setters for highlight color etc. in the timebarviewer have been deprecated but will still work
						with the every extension of the abstract grid renderer.
					</li>
					<li>
						the grid rederer now supports an alpha setting for the row selection
					</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2008-04-17 version 1.23">
				<ul>
					<li>
						made the timebarviewer friendlier to GUI-Designers (will hopefully not throw exceptions without a model) 
					</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2008-04-12 version 1.22">
				<ul>
					<li>
						Removed a dependency on Java 6 in the DefaultOverlapStrategy (Thanks Maarten)
					</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2008-04-06 version 1.21">
				<ul>
					<li>
						Fixed a bug that have been introduced with the autoscroll improvements: When using the grid snap dragging an interval
						has not been working.
					</li>
					<li>
						Th egrid snap provided by the IntervalModificators is now applied specifically: the first modificator that claims to
						be applicable will provide the grid snap. That makes it possible to use different grid snaps for different types
						of intervals.  
					</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2008-03-30 version 1.20">
				<ul>
					<li>
						Improved the resize detection/beviour: increasing the size of an interval has sometimes behaved unexpected,
						since the cursor had to be inside the interval.  
					</li>
					<li>
						Autoscrolling has been quite fast (since it was accellerating with the scrolling). This has been fixed. It is
						now possible to set the autoscrollDelta (in pixel) to ensure a controllable drag.  
					</li>
					<li>
						The timebar viewer will now drag all selected intervals if an interval is dragged and the option is enabled. 
						Autoscrolling is focussed on the 
						actual interval that is beeing dragged. If one of the intervals is not allowed to move to the new position, the
						whole drag is stopped. This behaviour can be enabled by setting setDragAllSelectedIntervals(true).    
					</li>
					
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2008-03-22 version 1.19">
				<ul>
					<li>
						Improved calendar example to show whole day appointments in header area. 
					</li>
					<li>
						Thanks go to Mathias Kurth for supplying an improved overlap calculation drastically 
						decreasing the time needed. This is especially helpful when handling huge quantities of intervals. (Added a link to his work
						on the usage page)
					</li>
					<li>
						Added a method to access the delegate in the viewers. Please note that the direct use of the delegate ist not ecouraged unless
						it is absolutely necessary.
					</li>
					<li>
						Added the RelationRenderer to render intervals having a relation (IRelationalInterval). 
						The relation rendering is work in progress.
					</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2007-12-27 version 1.18">
				<ul>
					<li>
						Internal version distributed with the jare calendar plugin 
					</li>
					<li>
						Bugfix: Interval modification failed in some special cases when using more than one IntervalModificator. 
					</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2007-12-22 version 1.17">
				<ul>
					<li>
						Bugfix: (non variable time scale) Scroll bounds have not been correct (small difference) corresponding to the model  
					</li>
					<li>
						Bugfix: just another small scrolling bug (using page steps with optimized scrolling)  
					</li>
					<li>
						Small change in the IntervalModificator interface (Sorry for that!) allowing better differentiation when using
						heterogenous models. (new Method isApplicable(...) to check whether the modificator is responsible -> just return true to preserve
						current behaviour.)  
					</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2007-11-20 version 1.16">
				<ul>
					<li>
						Bugfix: Scrolling with the time scroll bar using page steps failed when using optimized scrolling.  
					</li>
					<li>
						Bugfix: Single selections have been disabled by the selection behaviour if other intervals have been selected ... corrected  
					</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>

			<subsection name="2007-11-03 version 1.15">
				<ul>
					<li>
						Small improvements for scroll bars (right sized from the first appearance, max data check corrected)  
					</li>
					<li>
						Fixed several bugs when adding/removing nodes in a hierarchical model. (For test purposes the SWT Hierarchical example
						can now be switched to support drag and drop. Check the source code for the flag)  
					</li>
					<li>
						The default hierarchy renderer can now handle different label providers for different row/node implementations
					</li>
					<li>
						Improved selection behaviour: when doing a multiselection the next single selecting click did reset the multi selection. 
						This has been changed to do the single select on mouse release when intervals are selected. Thanks to Martin Schmidt
						for pointing that out.
					</li>
					<li>
						Added a new example showing events in a timeline fashion (s. screenshots). This has been inspired by the simile timeline
						for html pages (http://simile.mit.edu/timeline/).
					</li>
					<li>
						Externalized the strategy for calculating the overlap information. This allows implementing strategies that 
						can support lareg numbers of massively overlapping intervals without beeing too slow. See the timeline example for
						a sample of an alternative implementation. 
					</li>
					<li>
						BoxTimeScaleRenderer improved to handle variable scaling by adapting the scale
					</li>
					<li>
						Improved TimeScaleDragSupport to allow listening on diagram drags for scrolling
					</li>
					<li>
						Some small API extensions (non breaking)
					</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2007-09-22 version 1.14">
				<ul>
					<li>
						Fixed "row selection not working"-Bug  
					</li>
					<li>
						Fixed some Tooltip-Bugs (vertical). 
					</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2007-09-16 version 1.13">
				<ul>
					<li>
					Fixed a small bug that lead to a paint error for partly painted intervals when using variable scale
					</li>
					<li>
					The BoxTimeScaleRenderer now supports vertical orientation (might be time consuming since 
					vertical oriented text is)
					</li>
					<li>
					SWT: rendering outside the bounds given by the interval is now supported. See the extended renderer interface 
					TimeBarRenderer2 for details on how to do this from your renederer. This has a little impact on rendering optimizations
					so it can be turend off. See TimeBarViewer#setStrictClipTimeCheck for details. 
					</li>
					<li>
					SWT: Added an example doing some more fancy drawing. Demonstrating the new feature of drawing outside the 
					core interval space (FancyExample).
					</li>
					<li>
						Added a linking exception to the GPL license that allows linking to other freely available software (source code freely available)
					</li>

				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2007-08-19 version 1.12">
				<ul>
					<li>
						Added variable row heights/widths including the possibility to change the height/width of a row
						by dragging or the use of a calculation strategy (see ITimeBarViewstate).
					</li>
					<li>
						fixed some ends concerning vertical orientation (still the interface might be quite irritating when thinking
						vertical)
					</li>
					<li>
						SWT: printing fixed for windows, horizontal orientation, including support for variable row heights
					</li>

				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2007-07-18 version 1.11">
				<ul>
					<li>
						Fixed a bug that prevented the SWT version from drawing overlapped intervals without height correction. 
					</li>
					<li>
						Added a listener that is informed while intervals are modified by the users (ITimeBarChangeListener).
					</li>
					<li>
						Began a list of known usages of the timebars component (see <a href="tb_usages.html">usages</a>)
					</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2007-06-05 version 1.10">
				<ul>
					<li>
						<b>This version incorporates some bigger changes. Please regard it as a snapshot! Bug reports welcome.</b>
					</li>
					<li>
						introduced vertical orientation. Modifications have been done carefully, the semantics of some 
						API calls changed organically (rows now can be columns depending on the orientation ...). Support for
						vertical rendering has been added to most of the default renderers (Swing and SWT). (Some examples allow switching 
						orientation; a special example has been added: the calendar example, see screenshots).
						<p>
						Note: Hierachy renderers have not yet been enhanced to support vertical orientation --> so dont use a hierarchical 
						viewer with vertical orientation by now.
						</p>
					</li>
					<li>
						added support for internal row (column) scaling: if set the viewer adapts the row height to always display 
						a fixed number of rows (columns) (see setAutoRowScaling) 
					</li>
					<li>
						Scrolling optimizations fixed for SWT (tested Win, Linux/GTK, OSX/Intel). Scrolling optimizations are now <b>ENABLED</b>
						by default. If you experience any artefacts when scrolling, disable scroll optimizations (setOptimizedScrolling(false).)
					</li>
					<li>
						By mistake and stupidness the TimeBarViewerDelegate referenced SWT classes rendering it unusable for Swing. Fixed that
						(Thanks Tim!)
					</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2007-05-01 version 1.02">
				<ul>
					<li>
						SWT&amp;Swing: Introduced scrolling optimizations (copying previously drawn areas).
						The behaviour is switchable (setOptimizedScrolling) and defaults to false, since I noticed
						problems using SWT on Linux/GTK and OSX/Intel. However the
						performance gain on Windows XP is quite big if a lot or fancy diagrams are drawn.  
						For Swing the optimizations do work on all of the platforms.
						The scroling optimizations can not be 
						used together with a variable x scale.
					</li>
					<li>
						Added a method to the DefaultTimeBarRowModel that allows addition of more than one interval at a time. 
						(Please. note that the default implementation is an implementation that can easyly - and sometimes should -
						 be tailored for the needs of the concrete application). Also added methods for removal of more than one 
						 interval at a time.
					</li>
					<li>
						Fixed issues with non overlapped drawing and the dynamic use of an interval filter.
					</li>
					<li>
						Enhanced non overlapped drawing: in some cases the the result wasted some place.
					</li>
					<li>
						Fine tuned interaction between model and selection: Intervals removed from the mdoel will be removed
						from the selection. (This is not implemented for removeing lots of intervals at once, sice it would
						sacrify the peformance gained by removing all intervals at once)
					</li>
					<li>
						Fixed a small bug that occured when an interval was selected (apparent only on large scales, caused scrolling the 
						viewer without need).
					</li>
					<li>
						Fixed updating of the vertical scroll bar (to short in some situations)
					</li>
					<li>
						introduced the <a href="/timebars.addon/index.html">timebars.addon package</a>
					</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2007-03-12 version 1.01">
				<ul>
					<li>
						small correction to the default hierarchy renderer and the title renderer so that it
						accepts image descriptors instead of ressource paths
					</li>
					<li>a bug in the DefaultTimeScaleRenderer fixed (drawing was not complete)</li>
					<li>
						fixed a bug that prevented all intervals from beeing drawn when showing a long period
						of time (small pps)
					</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2007-02-18 version 1.0">
				<ul>
					<li>
						<b>Finally reached 1.0! Swing version is behind but the SWT version matters.</b>
					</li>
					<li>Wrote overview documentation to get users of the component started.</li>
					<li>
						Did testing using Linux/GTK and Mac OS X 10.4.5/Intel: Works, improved performance
					</li>
					<li>
						Added the renderer selection for different interval implementations to the core
						viewers (SWT and Swing)
					</li>
					<li>
						SWT: Added improved TimeScaleRenderer: The BoxTimeScaleRenderer is easy to modify and
						clear in appearance.
					</li>
					<li>
						SWT: revisited the printing support and did a lot of corrections, checked printing
						capability of the default renderers (added two PDF printouts to the screen shot page)
					</li>
					<li>Swing: added support for non-overlapping drawing of intervals</li>
					<li>Swing: added SwingOverlapExample</li>
					<li>
						Cleaned the example code from old rubbish (some code has never been touched since
						2004)
					</li>
					<li>Added millisecond accuracy to the interface (x scroll bar using milliseconds)</li>
					<li>Added interface for variable x scale to the main interface.</li>
					<li>Removed the obsolete setMajor/MinorTickMinutes methods from the viewers</li>
					<li>
						SWT: moved the gap renderer from the PDI example to main package as a default gap
						renderer (that has to be set if needed).
					</li>
					<li>
						fixed small bug: x scroll disappeared when scale has been changed on scrolled viewer
						making it impossible to scroll back to the beginning (only relevat when scaling
						changed)
					</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="version 0.991">
				<ul>
					<li>
						<b>Version 0.991 has been an internal evaluation version</b>
					</li>
					<li>Did some work on the variable scale feature.</li>
					<li>Added millisecond accuracy (SWT)</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2007-01-25 version 0.99">
				<ul>
					<li>
						Added support for drawing "ghosted" intervals and rows to the timebar viewer to
						support visual drag and drop.
					</li>
					<li>
						Colors for highlighting, row selection and row grid lines now configurable. Use alpha
						blending for highlighting resulting in smoother appearance.
					</li>
					<li>
						Selection delta for detecting marker selection/drag and interval edge detecting now
						configurable.
					</li>
					<li>
						Fixed some unclean behaviour when resizing intervals that resulted in the experience
						that in some cases the selection seemed a bit unsharp (selection for resizing: cursor
						has been set to resize cursor outside the interval).
					</li>
					<li>Internal drag operations can now be canceled with ESC</li>
					<li>Improved the default title render: now supports a background image.</li>
					<li>Improved the default hierarchy render: now supports images as symbols.</li>
					<li>Further improvements of the documentation (Still some work to do)</li>
					<li>
						Improved SwtOverlapExample to support and demonstrate possible variant of implementing
						drag&amp;drop
					</li>
					<li>
						Improved SwtHierarchyExample: added more options to play with and demonstrate images
						in the hierarchy renderer
					</li>
					<li>
						The DefaultRenderer for intervals now checks the registered renderers by interfaces
						and superclasses eliminating the need to use concrete classes for matching special
						renderers
					</li>
					<li>
						The limiting lines determing the width of the hierarchy area and the width of the
						header area (y axis) can now be dragged by the user. This behaviour can be disabled.
					</li>
					<li>
						Fixed some minor bugs (probably never noticed by anyone):
						<ul>
							<li>selection using space did not work on SWT version</li>
							<li>printing without time scale caused NPE</li>
							<li>printing missed the title</li>
						</ul>
					</li>
					<li>
						Added some methods to the DefaultTimeBarModel making it easier to modify data therein.
					</li>
					<li>Updated status page</li>

				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2007-01-06 version 0.982">
				<ul>
					<li>
						<b>
							Version 0.982 is another snapshot on the way to the Version 1.0 release, this is
							almost feature complete
						</b>
					</li>
					<li>
						Corrected bug: When rows have been added to an AddingTimeBarRow that did not contain
						any intervals this has been handled incorrectly. Improved that class in some aspects.
						(Thanks to Shahar Maoz for pointing out the bug)
					</li>
					<li>
						Corrected bug: In some cases with high pixel per second setting the drawing failed
						until the scrollbar has been moved (Thanks to Shahar Maoz for pointing out the bug)
					</li>
					<li>Corrected the project path and plugin name: de.jaret.util.ui.timebars</li>
					<li>
						Made the TimeBarIntervalFilter a PropertyObservable. Introduced AbstractTimeBarFilter.
					</li>
					<li>Further improvements of the documentation</li>
					<li>
						Included the experimental feature of different scalings on the xaxis for dedicated
						intervals. See the swthierarchy example for a usage example.
					</li>

				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2006-08-22 version 0.981">
				<ul>
					<li>
						<b>
							Version 0.981 is another snapshot on the way to the Version 1.0 release, this is
							almost feature complete
						</b>
					</li>
					<li>
						Documentation: Improved parts of the javadoc, added a brief overview describing the
						examples, added a document describing the architecture and containing some little
						howtos.
					</li>

				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2006-05-03 version 0.98">
				<ul>
					<li>
						<b>
							Version 0.98 is another snapshot on the way to the Version 1.0 release, this is
							almost feature complete
						</b>
					</li>
					<li>
						SWT: fixed some bugs in handling the rendering and dragging of multiple overlapping
						intervals.
					</li>
					<li>
						fixed some bugs that were introduced with the soft scrolling, causing selection by
						click to fail in some cases (hope I got them all by now)
					</li>
					<li>
						SWT: enhanced hierarchy handling (togglingArea, row selection in hierachy, label from
						label provider will be rendererd by DefaultHierarchyRenderer)
					</li>
					<li>
						SWT: added a global renderer allowing the rendering of elements in between the
						individual intervals (e.g. relations); see the SwtHierarchy example.
					</li>
					<li>SWT: added zoom in/out using ctrl+mousewheeel</li>
					<li>
						SWT: refactored support for standard actions to be in util.actions (the handling of
						predefined actions may change in future versions)
					</li>
					<li>did some code cleanup and optimizations</li>

				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2006-02-17 version 0.97">
				<ul>
					<li>
						<b>Version 0.97 is another snapshot on the way to the Version 1.0 release</b>
						- it may contain some open ends.
					</li>
					<li>
						SWT: introduced focus handling: a focus mark can be moved by the cursor keys if the
						viewer has the focus. Keyboard control: shift+left/right=grow left/right,
						alt+left/right=schrink left/right, ctrl+left/right=move left/right, SPACE=select,
						ctrl+SPACE=select multiple.
					</li>
					<li>
						SWT: TimeBarViewer now implements ISelectionProvider for better RCP/JFace integration
					</li>
					<li>
						SWT: Introduced TBViewer as extension of JFace.StructuredViewer for better JFace
						integration (experimental)
					</li>
					<li>changed build to maven2</li>
					<li>
						TimeBarRowSorters and -filters are now PropertyObservables. (Quick fix for existing
						Filters and Sorters: extend PropertyObservableBase!)
					</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2005-10-03 version 0.96">
				<ul>
					<li>
						<b>Version 0.96 is a snapshot on the way to the Version 1.0 release</b>
						- it may contain some open ends.
					</li>
					<li>SWT: Introduced a title renderer.</li>
					<li>
						SWT: changed the rendering subsystem (sorry: includes the renderers) to support
						printing with a minimal effort. Enabled the default renderers for printing. Use the
						TimeBarPrinter to print the graph.
					</li>
					<li>SWT: introduced context menu handling</li>
					<li>SWT + Swing: introduced smooth scrolling (showign a clipped row as the top row)</li>
					<li>SWT: introduced rendering of a title</li>
					<li>Cleaned the TimebarMarker interface.</li>
					<li>SWT: introduced the TimebarMarkerRenderer for rendering of markers.</li>
					<li>SWT: improved hierarchy renderer</li>
					<li>
						SWT: added the dispose() method to all renderers to support disposal of resources.
					</li>
					<li>
						Improved default timescale and grid renderers (scaling, labelling). SWT versions now
						support marking of weekends and holidays (with a HolidayEnumerator, see jaretutil
						package)
					</li>
					<li>
						Separated the view state of the hierarchical model (expanded/collapsed) from the model
						itself thus allowing different views on the same hierarchical model. This refactoring
						did cause some major changes. The introduced HierarchicalViewState does not support
						view states identified by a path. This causes the state of equal nodes in a model to
						be the same.
					</li>
					<li>
						Removed the accessor for the delegate. Maybe there are still some methods missing ->
						report.
					</li>
					<li>Switched to SWT 3.1 Release</li>
					<li>SWT: forceFocus() on click -> mouse wheel will scroll vertically</li>


				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2005-06-04 version 0.95">
				<ul>
					<li>Corrected some bugs ;-)</li>
					<li>
						Introduced AddingTimeBarRow and AddingTimeBarNode for hierachical view (see hierarchy
						example)
					</li>
					<li>
						Default renderers for TimeBars now support registration for additional renderers for
						easy differentiated rendering of different intervals
					</li>
					<li>Cleaned and enhanced handling of the scrollbars (page increment etc.)</li>
					<li>
						Enhanced default timescalerenderer and default gridrenderer to scale. The
						TimeScaleRenderer now supports top and bottom placement.
					</li>
					<li>Added autoscrolling for visual editing and markers.</li>
					<li>
						Corrected tooltip behaviour (toooltips will show up for swt version after clicking the
						mouse), timebar markers will show their description as the tooltip.
					</li>

				</ul>
			</subsection>


			<subsection name="2005-05-07 version 0.94">
				<ul>
					<li>refactorings (JDK 1.5, ++)</li>
					<li>changed build process to maven</li>
					<li>
						introduced an interface for the row header (will force changes in existing
						applications)
					</li>
					<li>added support for a hierarchical model as an extension to the flat list of rows</li>
					<li>
						added support for changing intervals (drag an interval inside its row, resize an
						interval), controlled by IntervalModificators that allow/disallow changes
					</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2004-12-23 version 0.92">
				<ul>
					<li>
						changed the JaretDate/JaretDateFormatter to use a single JaretDateFormatter for all
						JaretDates. This change decreases the memory usage but restricts applications to one
						Formatter.
					</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2004-12-21 version 0.91">
				<ul>
					<li>first public release</li>
					<li>some minor bug fixes and refactoring</li>
					<li>
						refactoring of the class JaretDate: i8n, introduced a localized JaretDateFormatter as
						a delegate to do convenient textual output
					</li>
					<li>
						correction of the Swing DefaultGridRenderer: minor ticks were not painted up to the
						first major tick.
					</li>
					<li>
						the delegate is still accessible; the most common methods can now be called on the
						viewers itself.
					</li>
					<li>added some documentation</li>
					<li>included (bad) example code in the distribution</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="2004-11-09 version 0.90">
				<ul>
					<li>non-public pre release</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
